Snapcraft makes it easy to package and distribute your node applications to Linux users.
If you don't already have the snapcraft command, you'll need to install it. There's a link in the description below
First we need to check the application name is available in the store and register it for our use
If the name is taken don't worry just choose another one
Now we'll create a template snapcraft yaml which will edit to describe the application
Add in the metadata users will see when searching the store for your application
If you had to register a different name earlier be sure to use that here
Now, add a part to describe how your application is built.
We use the node.js plugin snapcraft knows how to handle nodejs applications
We'll start with Devmode which means the application is unconfined. We can tighten that up later
Finally we add an app stanza to define the commands contained in the snap.
That’s it. Now we can create the snap with the snapcraft command.
Install and test the unsigned package locally with snap install
And push to the store with snapcraft push
Great! Now you can tell your community to snap install your application
Find out more at snapcraft dot io